A Guide to the Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1890–2008, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records 1890–2008, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1995–019
10 boxes; 6.8 cu. ft.
The Daughters of the American Revolution (D.A.R.) was formed in 1890 as an organization to perpetuate the memory and spirit of the men and women who achieved American Indepedence, to encourage historical research in relation to the Revolution, and to promote the celebration of all patriotic anniversaries. The records consist of rosters, D.A.R. magazines, contitutions and by–laws, minutes and membership ledgers, yearbooks, scrapbooks, news bulletins, obituaries of members, and the original charter of the Alleghany Chapter.
Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The initial collection was donated to Special Collections in July 1995.
Accruals
Additional materials were donated in May 1997, June 1998, November 2000, and April 2009.
Historical Information
The Daughters of the American Revolution (D.A.R.) was formed in 1890 as an organization to "perpetuate the memory and spirit of the men and women who achieved American Independence, by the acquisition and protection of historical spots, and the erection of monuments; by the encouragement of historical research in relation to the Revolution and the publication of its results; by the preservation of documents and relics, and of the records of the individual services of the Revolutionary soldiers and patriots, and by the promotion of celebrations of all patriotic anniversaries." The motto is "God, Home, and Country." Membership in the D.A.R. is eligible to "any woman 18 years or older, regardless of race, religion, or ethnic background, who can prove lineal descent from a patriot of the American Revolution." "Patriot" includes several types of military, civil, or other service in the course of the Revolution.
The Alleghany Chapter was organized in Blacksburg, Virginia, in January 1911. The first officers of the chapter were Mrs. Paul Barringer, Regent; Miss Ellen McDonald, Vice–Regent; Mrs. Alexander Black, Treasurer; Mrs. J.S.A. Johnson, Recording Secretary; Mrs. Nelson Mayo, Corresponding Secretary; and Mrs. James Otey, Registrar and Chair of the History Committee. Many of the charter members were descended from pioneers who held land in the New River section of the Alleghany Mountains, now known as "Trans–Alleghany Pioneers." The original members chose the name "Alleghany" over an individual hero of the Revolutionary War as their name, to preserve the colonial history and traditions of the region.
The chapter members erected several markers in Blacksburg and the region memorializing people and events of its colonial history. Most noteworthy is the marker at Barger Fort on Ribbles Spring in Christiansburg, on the grave of Revolutionary soldier and early settler Giles Thomas in the Blacksburg Cemetery, and in memory of Col. William Patton and the pioneers who lost their lives in the Drapers Meadow Massacre in 1755, placed near Smithfield Plantation in Blacksburg.
For additional information see:
Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution
Daughters of the American Revolution
Scope and Content
The Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records contain several types of materials including bound books and ledgers, published bulletins and magazines, conference and committee programs, scrapbooks, and historical news–clippings. The collection also contains the original charter and framed awards.
Two boxes of the collection consist of bound books or ledgers. Box 1 contains Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution rosters from the founding of the DAR in 1890 through the mid–1930s, and a National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution lineage book from 1898. Box 9 holds Alleghany Chapter ledgers: membership records, 1911–1991; meeting minutes, 1911–2004; and financial records, 1957–1986.
The collection houses the Virigina DAR News Bulletin from 1962–1991 and the Daughters of the American Revolution Magazine from 1928–1932, 1987. It also contains incomplete runs of Alleghany Chapter yearbooks and supplements from 1947 to 2000 and the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks from 1980 to 1991.
The programs in the collection relate to chapter, state, and national Daughters of the American Revolution conferences and committees. Examples include materials from Alleghany Chapter annual meetings, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Continental Congress programs and centennial celebration literature, and Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution State Conferences.
The collection includes several scrapbooks and folders of loose news–clippings. The scrapbooks feature photographs of local and national events, programs, and correspondence related to scholarships and service. Scrapbooks in this collection date from 1931 through 2008. The news–clippings often relate to individual members of the Alleghany Chapter, as well as to chapter projects and interests (i.e. the Preston family, the Smithfield plantation, and grave/memorial markers). Clippings in the collection range from the 1920s to the 1970s and come from a variety of local and regional newspapers.
An oversize box (Box 8) contains the original framed charter for the Alleghany Chapter from 1911.The application for the charter is also a part of the collection and can be found in Box 10. Box 8 also houses several framed awards the chapter received between 1942 and 1953.
Arrangement
The initial donation (July 1995) and first accrual (May 1997) are arranged chronologically. Later accruals (1998–2009) are arranged chronologically by type of material.
Contents List
- Box 1 1890–1958
  - Roster of Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution, bound book, 1890–1958. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Roster of Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution, bound book, 1892–1936. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Lineage Book, 1898. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Box 2 1908–1989
  - Early history of Daughters of the American Revolution booklet, 1908. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution magazines, 1928–1932. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution citizenship, protocol, and procedure manuals, and Constitution and By–laws (Folder 1 of 2), 1940–1989. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution citizenship, protocol, and procedure manuals, and Constitution and By–laws (Folder 2 of 2), 1940–1989. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks and supplements, 1947–1977 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Supplements to the Roster of the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution, 1959–1965. (Box-folder 2:6)
- Box 3 1960–1995
  - History of the Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution, 1960–1987. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Virginia DAR News Bulletin, 1962–1991 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - History of Chapter Names, Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution, bound book, 1964. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Placement of markers on graves of revolutionary soldiers, newspaper articles, 1968–1974. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Allegheny Chapter National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution annual meeting programs, newspaper articles, 1969–1987. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Draper Meadow massacre marker, 1971. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Grave marking ceremony for Colonel William Preston and wife, Susanna Smith, 1973. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Placement of markers on graves of Daughters of the American Revolution members, 1976–1980. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks and supplements, 1977–1995. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Box 4 1978–1994, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, programs, and papers, 1978–1992. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution State Conference Programs, 1981–1985. (Box-folder 4:2)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Continental Congress programs, 1981–1988. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution directories of committees, 1982–1992. (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Public relations literature, 1984–1987. (Box-folder 4:5)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution centennial celebration literature, 1989–1990. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Obituaries of Daughters of the American Revolution members, 1992–1993. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Photographs from Daughters of the American Revolution meetings, 1992–1994. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution schools, n.d. (Box-folder 4:9)
- Box 5 1980–1991
  - Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks (Folder 1 of 3), 1980–1983. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks (Folder 2 of 3), 1985–1988. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution yearbooks (Folder 3 of 3), 1989–1991. (Box-folder 5:3)
- Box 9 1911–2004
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution membership record book, 1911–1964. (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution membership record book, 1939–1975. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution membership record book, 1977–1991. (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1911–1926. (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1926–1950. (Box-folder 9:5)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1951–1966. (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1967–1987. (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1987–1994. (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution minutes ledger, 1995–2004. (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution financial records, 1957–1976. (Box-folder 9:10)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution financial records, 1962–1967, 1968–1973, 1973–1979, 1979–1986. (Box-folder 9:11)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution financial records, 1977–1984. (Box-folder 9:12)
- Box 10 1909–2008, n.d.
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution charter application and founding materials, 1909–1910, n.d. (Box-folder 10:1)
  - National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution pamphlets and magazines, 1910, 1924, 1987. (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1928–1961. (Box-folder 10:3)
  - Virginia and North Carolina Daughters of the American Revolution programs, 1931, 1948. (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Miscellaneous papers and correspondence, 1934–1967, n.d. (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution awards scrapbook (Folder 1 of 3), 1962–1984. (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution awards scrapbook (Folder 2 of 3), 1985–1995. (Box-folder 10:7)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution awards scrapbook—yearbooks and supplements (Folder 3 of 3), 1989–1992. (Box-folder 10:8)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution supplement, 1999–2000. (Box-folder 10:9)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 1 of 3), 1999–2005. (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 2 of 3), 1999–2005. (Box-folder 10:11)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 3 of 3), 1999–2005. (Box-folder 10:12)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 1 of 4), 2005–2008. (Box-folder 10:13)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 2 of 4), 2005–2008. (Box-folder 10:14)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 3 of 4), 2005–2008. (Box-folder 10:15)
  - Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook (Folder 4 of 4), 2005–2008. (Box-folder 10:16)
- Box 6 (Oversize) 1931–1973
  - Scrapbooks, 1931–1980, 1953–1963, 1964–1971, 1971–1973. (Box 6)
- Box 7 (Oversize) 1980–1992
  - Scrapbooks, 1980–1987, 1989–1992. (Box 7)
- Box 8 (Oversize) 1912–1953
  - Framed charter of the Allegheny Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution, 1912. (Box 8)
  - Framed awards, 1942–1953. (Box 8)